Daf is Ayin Tes. We start from
the top, the bottom of עין ט'
עמוד ב'. Now we are moving a
little bit back into things that sound
a little more like Zevachim. We're talking
about the actual slaughtering of the Korban,
but again, the Todah presents a very
interesting hybrid because it has a Korban
element and the Mincha as it were,
bread element. Although as I said, questionable,
obviously the Gemara is treating it as
a Mincha, but it's Kodshim Kalim and
not Kodshei Kodashim. It's not thrown on
its own, so you know, it's not
exactly a Mincha. Anyway, and that's what
we're focusing on is how the Todah
relates to the bread. So last day,
yesterday we saw that the slaughtering of
the Korban is what gives Kedushah to
the bread. And now we are going
to continue on that discussion. So let's
take a look. שחטה חוץ לזמנו וחוץ
למקומו, if the Todah was slaughtered—now again,
this Chutz Lizmano, Chutz Limkomo, as you
probably remember from Zevachim, does not literally
mean in the wrong place or at
the wrong time. Actually hard to imagine
what the wrong time would be; I
guess it could be at night. Anyway,
but it means with a thought of
the wrong place or the wrong time.
So it's a Piggul thought or a
Chutz Limkomo thought which is analogous to
a Piggul thought. So basically, we said
that the slaughtering of the Todah sanctifies
the bread. What happens if the Todah
is slaughtered incorrectly, it was a Pasul?
So here, interestingly, Kiddesh Halachem, the bread
does become Kadosh. Kadosh Venifsal, which is
the worst of the scenarios, which means
that it's sanctified, now the Korban is
no good. If the Korban is no
good, the bread is no good and
you can't use it for anything else.
Okay, so that's Kiddesh Halachem. Shachata Venimtzeit
Treifah, but this is in contrast to
if the Korban was slaughtered and it
was a Treifah, which also means it's
Pasul, Lo Kiddesh Halachem, the bread is
not sanctified. What is the difference? The
difference is actually obvious, pretty obvious, which
the Gemara will say explicitly. If the
Shechitah was never Kasher to begin with—the
Psul occurred before the Shechitah—so the Shechitah
was meaningless from the get-go, it was
already a Treifah, then the Shechitah did
not sanctify the bread. If it didn't
sanctify the bread, that's better, now you
could use the bread for some other
Korban. If, however, the Shechitah was Kasher,
or the Psul didn't predate the Shechitah,
the Psul was somehow in the Shechitah,
it was this Psul of Piggul, a
wrong thought or whatever, but the act
of Shechitah is Kasher, it's Kiddesh Halachem.
There was a Korban problem that adds
a Psul to it, so it's Kadosh
but now it's Pasul, like I said,
the worst of both cases. Now yes,
it bothers you because—I don't know if
it's a matter of predating, I think
it's sort of like, you know, you
didn't have mind for this, so it's
not even considered. Mind doesn't matter so
much. Let's say you do Hagramah and
you validate it through the act of
Shechitah. That would also Lo Kiddesh Halachem,
because it wasn't a Ma'aseh Shechitah. So
if it's a Treifa or let's say
the Shechitah is itself technically Psul just
in terms of the physical act, that's,
you're right. The case of Treifa is
an easy case because it's not a
Kasher Shechitah. Or if it's a, or
if it's like Michael says, you know,
you put pressure on it, you did
something that would have made it Treif,
you know, in normal Kashrut laws. It's
not a Kasher Shechitah, obviously Lo Kiddesh
Halachem. The more interesting case we're going
to see in a minute will be
a Mum case where it's a Kasher
Shechitah but it's a Korban problem. Okay,
so let's look at the next case
and that'll help maybe clarify. You're thinking
is it a Treifa then? Well, let's
take a look. Let's take a look.
שחטה ונמצאת בעלת מום, you slaughtered and
then you realized that it had a
Mum. Now this Mum predated the Shechitah
but you weren't aware of it. רבי
אליעזר אומר קידש, you did sanctify the
bread, וחכמים אומרים לא קידש, you did
not sanctify. So what is this debate
about? So it could be along the
lines, you know, that Michael and I
were discussing a minute ago. It could
be exactly this: the Shechitah as an
act of Shechitah, like if you were
to judge it through a Kashrut lens,
was kosher. The problem was a Korban
problem. It had a Mum, or like
the other problem, it was with a
wrong Machshavah. But the act of Shechitah
is Kasher, it's Kiddesh Halachem. There was
a Korban problem that adds a Psul
to it, so it's Kadosh but now
it's Pasul, like I said, the worst
of both cases. That makes a lot
of sense in terms of the position
that Ba'alat Mum is Kiddesh Halachem. What
we're going to see in the Gemara
is that the position that a Ba'alat
Mum is Lo Kiddesh Halachem basically does
this issue of tie predating or not
predating. If the Mum predated, then when
you get to the Shechitah you say
at this moment the Shechitah is meaningless,
it already has a Mum. I don't
care whether it's a Korban problem or
another problem, the Shechitah is meaningless, it
already has a Mum. So therefore the
Shechitah can't be Mekadesh. But if when
you got to the Shechitah everything was
okay, and then your thought invalidated it,
so the Shechitah is a meaningful Shechitah,
it's just you had a problem of
your thought. Therefore, that gets you into
the worst-case scenario where because the Shechitah
was okay it's Kiddesh, but you introduced
the Psul, so it's Kadosh and it's
Pasul. So just clarifying the difference between
Treifa and Mum, what—? Yeah, Treifa is
like a Kashrut issue, Treifa means like
it has a hole in the lung.
A Mum is an external blemish. Well
right, that's one of the ways of
defining it, but yes, it's some type
of an internal injury that will let's
say make it a Treifa in normal
Kashrut laws. It's not a Kasher Shechitah.
Obviously Lo Kiddesh Halachem. The more interesting
case we're going to see in a
minute will be a Mum case where
it's a Kasher Shechitah but it's a
Korban problem. Okay, so let's look at
the next case and that'll help maybe
clarify. But a Mum they could see
before they—? But they might have missed
it or it— is under this, under
the thigh where the flap of the
skin was covering it up. They weren't
paying close attention. Okay, the Gemara actually
is going to talk about a cataract
of the eye, like some mum that's
not blatant. Why should they be different
between a treifah and a mum? Because
a treifah so, like I said, one
way to explain it which is not
the way the Gemara's going to, but
I think is the simpler explanation, is
that a treifah because it's a it's
a normal kashrus problem, a treifah means
it wasn't a kasher shechitah. The shechitah
didn't do anything, it didn't make the
meat permissible, whereas a mum, the shechitah
was kosher. It's just that it was
a korban problem. A mum is about
what's a korban, it's not a general
problem of animals. It's not acceptable, but
if we want to say, did the
was there an act of a shechitah
at the Beis HaMikdash it would have
been okay. So if the question is,
was there an act of shechitah that
sanctified the bread, obviously the korban is
pasul, but what we want to know
is, did the bread become kadosh? To
answer if the bread became kadosh, we
don't want to just know if the
the bread can become kadosh even if
the korban is pasul, like in the
case of the machshavah. The question is,
you need the shechitah to sanctify the
bread. Did we have a shechitah? So
that's how I would frame the mum
issue. That's not how the Gemara's going
to frame the mum issue. Okay, let's
finish the mishnah and then we'll see
what the Gemara does. Okay, shelo lishma.
Now, if it is did I skip
a line? No. shelo lishma. Let's say
you slaughtered it without the right intention
to be a Todah. So what do
we normally say? Actually there we say
the korban is kasher, but לא עלו
לבעלים לשם חובה. Nevertheless, וכן איל מלואים
וכן שני כבשי עצרת, we're going to
do two other cases where there's bread
that is coming as a result of
the animal korban, the eil hamiluim, which
is interesting, the recent Mishnayos have been
interested in that. That was like the
first case where the Torah had a
shelamim brought with bread coming along. And
the shnei kavsei atzeres, which actually also
are shelamim together with bread. So these
are all very linked phenomena, right? They
are shelamim with bread where the focus
where you know, where the bread somehow
is being the that the bringing of
the korban somehow sanctifies the bread. So
in all of those cases, sheshachtan shelo
lishman, if you do it shelo lishmo,
lo kidesh halechem, the bread does not
become kadosh. Not because the korban is
pasul, but we learned out yesterday it
says על זבח תודת שלמיו, it has
to be slaughtered as a Todah and
only then it kidesh halechem. One could
say the reason is because what links
the bread to the animal, what defines
them, you know, as somehow units, so
the slaughtering of the animal sanctifies the
bread is its identity as a Todah
or its identity as the shnei kavsei
atzeres, right? If it was some other
korban, the bread would be irrelevant. So
if you are not slaughtering it with
that lishmah, then the bread cannot be
linked and the bread cannot be sanctified.
Well, given so you're saying you're saying
it would be different than let's say
I do it lishmah but instead of
thinking having you in mind, having him
in mind? Excellent question. Yeah, shelo leshem
ba'alim. I think shelo leshem ba'alim it
would be kidesh halechem. I'd have to
check that up, but that's a great
question. I would say it would be
kidesh. And remember the pasuk is על
זבח תודה לשלמיו. It means your shelamav.
Okay, it's a good question. I would
have to look it up, but I
would think I would incline to say
I'm inclined to say yes. I think
that the you know, you could just
say it's gezeiras hakatuv, it has to
be lishmah for the kidesh, but I
really think it's because that the lechem
only relates to it because of its
particular identity. So your case of lo
leshem ba'alim is a good question. Okay,
so now let's take a look at
the Gemara how the Gemara explains what
type of shechitah is mekadesh the bread
and what type is not. Masnisin mani?
Who is our mishnah? Rabbi Meir. It's
Rabbi Meir de'tanya. And now we're going
to have a braisa that will say
that it's the position of Rabbi Meir
and also clarifies the logic behind the
mishnah. Zeh haklal, this is the principle.
כל שפסולו קודם שחיטה. Now you see
why I'm getting at it Michael. Any
any invalidity that predated the shechitah, lo
kidesh halechem, the bread does not become
kadosh because by the time you got
up to the shechitah, it was already
pasul, so the shechitah cannot be meaningful
to be to sanctify the bread. Achar
shechitah, after the shechitah, after really doesn't
mean after, really sort of means not
predating, because obviously there's a psul that
comes during the shechitah. But if it
does not I mean not predating, if
it does not predate the shechitah, kidesh
halechem, then when you got to the
shechitah everything was okay, so the shechitah
sanctifies the bread. And now we're going
to give the examples. Actually now we're
going to go the reverse order of
the way we just presented it. שחטה
חוץ לזמנו וחוץ למקומו, if you shechted
it with the wrong thought in mind,
wrong time or wrong place, kidesh halechem,
the bread does become kadosh because there
the psul did not predate. The psul
came at the moment, but it's not
predated and therefore it is considered that
the shechitah was a meaningful shechitah. Shachtah,
by the way, but to just clarify
the point Michael raised, if the shechitah
really was a bad shechitah in terms
of just a kashrus bad shechitah, like
you applied pressure or something, obviously lo
kidesh because then it wasn't even an
act of a shechitah. But if it
was the korban was kasher and it
was an act of a shechitah and
then a psul was introduced, even if
it was during the shechitah, the shechitah
is still considered a ma'aseh shechitah and
it's kidesh halechem. Okay, or a sufficient
shechitah to be mekadesh halechem. Shachtah venimtzes
treifah, if the shechitah was while it
was a treifah, lo kidesh halechem, the
bread does not become sanctified because it
predated. shechita. Now we look at the
top of עין ח עמוד א. Now,
and this is the yishuv in our
Mishna, the debate: שחטה ונמצא בעל מום,
just shachta and it was a baal
mum. רבי אליעזר אומר קידש, רבי יהושע
אומר לא קידש. So that's the debate
of Rabbi Eliezer and Rabbi Yehoshua. And
now if we're framing the issue as
predating or not predating, it's hard to
understand why Rabbi Eliezer says kidesh because
the mum predated the shechita. So we'll
discuss that in a minute. Divrei Rabbi
Meir. That's how Rabbi Meir understood. Rabbi
Meir understood we're going to see that
everybody knew there was a debate of
Rabbi Eliezer and Rabbi Yehoshua about the
parameters here and Rabbi Meir understood that
their debate was local was about the
issue of the baal mum which is
our Mishna. But now we're going to
see that there's another version of what
the debate was. Amar Rabbi Yehuda, so
Rabbi Yehuda said back to Rabbi Meir,
לא נחלקו רבי אליעזר ורבי יהושע על
שחטה ונמצאת טרפה. First of all you're
right, nobody debated the case of a
treifa, shelo kidesh, everybody agrees the bread
is not sanctified because it wasn't a
good shechita. It was treifa already before
you got there. ועל חוץ לזמנו שקידש
and nobody disagrees that if it was
a problem about a thought of a
pigul that it was kidesh halachem. Okay,
that everybody also agrees to because the
psul was only introduced at the moment
of the shechita. But not only that,
those are the two points you Rabbi
Meir already said, but even the baal
mum case, ועל בעל מום שלא קידש.
Everybody agrees with the baal mum lo
kidesh. Why? Because based on the way
the Gemara's framed it, a baal mum
is same as a treifa because the
issue is predating the shechita. So you're
wrong, they did not debate a baal
mum that predated the shechita and everybody
agrees it's no good. Veal mah nechelku,
what was the debate? Al chutz limkomo,
a thought problem but not a pigul
thought chutz lizmano but a chutz limkomo.
And this is quite fascinating. We learned
the entire Masechet Zevachim and chutz lizmano
and chutz limkomo were like Siamese twins,
right? One was d'oraita and the other
was d'rabbanan. No, it wasn't d'oraita d'rabbanan,
one was karet and the other was
not karet. One was pigul and karet,
the other was not karet. But in
terms of other than that's a big
difference, other than the karet issue, the
punishment, the severity, the cases in which
they operated, the ways in which they
invalidated were always the exact same. We
are finally you know you had to
get through all of Zevachim and three
quarters of Menachot to find this discussion
about funny again the way you know
places things are not always in their
place, the possibility that chutz limkomo in
some cases can have a different scope
than chutz lizmano. So let's take a
look. That's what he says they debated.
על מה נחלקו על חוץ למקומו, when
the thought is to eat in the
wrong place. שרבי אליעזר אומר קידש, רבי
יהושע אומר לא קידש. Rabbi Eliezer says
it is the bread is kadosh just
like chutz lizmano, just like a pigul
thought and Rabbi Yehoshua said no, that's
different than pigul, the bread is not
kadosh. So that's pretty interesting. Why is
that different? So let's take a look
and here he has, this is fascinating,
Rabbi Yehuda had a whole version of
their debate not just with opinions but
with a whole back and forth. Okay
and again this is an interesting question
in general about mesorah. It's not only
that like Rabbi Yehuda remembers their debate
to be about this topic and Rabbi
Meir remembers it about baal mum. I
remember their debate they were debating baal
mum, no I remember they were debating
chutz limkomo. No, we're going to see
that Rabbi Yehuda has a whole narrative
of their debate with a whole series
of proofs back and forth. So it
raises like interesting questions about where did
these different traditions develop from. Okay so
let's take a look. So amar Rabbi
Yehoshua, so here's still within Rabbi Yehuda
his version of their debate. Rabbi Yehoshua
said to Rabbi Eliezer okay, הואיל וחוץ
למקומו פסול ובעל מום פסול. Look, did
I skip a line? I think I
skipped a line. Amar Rabbi Eliezer, here's
Rabbi Eliezer explaining his argument why chutz
lizmano and chutz limkomo should be the
same. הואיל וחוץ לזמנו פסול. Chutz lizmano
is a psul, that's pigul. vechutz limkomo
pasul and chutz limkomo is a psul
also very analogous about a wrong thought.
מה חוץ לזמנו קידש אף חוץ למקומו
קידש. So the same way chutz lizmano
the bread is sanctified so the same
with the psul of chutz limkomo. So
amar Rabbi Yehoshua, so Rabbi Yehoshua said
back no, I'll compare it to another
thing. הואיל וחוץ למקומו פסול ובעל מום
פסול. So chutz limkomo is an invalidity
and a baal mum is an invalidity.
מה בעל מום לא קידש אף חוץ
למקומו לא קידש. The same way a
blemish does not if you shachted the
animal with a blemish the bread is
not sanctified so the same is true
with chutz limkomo. Now that's a really
bad comparison, right? How are they similar?
One predated the other didn't predate, one
is a thought, one is physical. Compare
the thought to the thought. All right
so that's where we're going to get.
Okay so let's keep on going. Obviously
here the weight of the argument seems
to be on Rabbi Eliezer's side, right?
Chutz lizmano chutz limkomo are pair. But
let's keep on going. Okay it gets
more interesting. Okay so אמר לו רבי
אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer said back to him
what are you talking about? אני דמיתיו
לחוץ לזמנו ואתה דמיתו לבעל מום. I've
compared it to a chutz lizmano, you
compare it to a baal mum. Nireh
lemi domeh, let's see which one is
it more similar to. אם דומה לחוץ
לזמנו נדוננו מחוץ לזמנו. If it's more
similar to chutz lizmano we'll learn it
from chutz lizmano. from chutz lizmano. אם
דומה לבעל מום, if it's more similar
to ba'al mum, nidonennu mi-ba'al mum, then
we can derive it from a ba'al
mum. So let's have the debate now,
let's shift the debate to the question
of which is it more similar to,
and that'll determine what the halacha is.
So התחיל רבי אליעזר לדון. So Rabbi
Eliezer started making, analyzing or arguing. דנים
פסול מחשבה מפסול מחשבה, you derive a
case where it's an invalidity based on
thought from an invalidity based on thought,
ואין דנים פסול מחשבה מפסול הגוף, you
don't derive an invalidity of thought, chutz
limkomo, from a blemish which is a
physical invalidity. That's reasonable. So התחיל רבי
יהושע לדון. So Rabbi Yehoshua no, he
derived it his way. דנים פסול שאין
בו כרת מפסול שאין בו כרת, chutz
limkomo doesn't have kares, that's the one
way it's different from chutz lizmano, and
you learn it out from a mum,
which is also a problem that doesn't
have kares ever attached to it, v'ein
danim, and you don't learn out... I
lost my place, davka yochiach, that's why,
hold on, I just lost my place.
Okay, where am I? Oh, ואל יוכיח
חוץ לזמנו שפסול שיש בו כרת. And
let's not learn it out from chutz
lizmano which has kares. Now of course
that's who cares, that's like a trivial
point. The severity of it is not
really speaking to the character of it.
So that does not seem to be
so relevant. But here comes his better
argument. ועוד נדוננו משלא לשמו. I'll concede
to you that mum is a bad
model, but I have a better model
to learn it from. Let's learn it
from the case of shelo lishmo. Why
should we learn it from shelo lishmo?
שפסול מחשבה ואין בו כרת. That is
another example of a machshava psul and
there's no kares. So why are you
going to learn it from chutz lizmano?
I have another machshava psul that the
bread is not sanctified. What did the
mishna say? If you slaughtered it shelo
lishmo, everybody agrees the bread is not
sanctified. So let's learn chutz limkomo from
shelo lishmo. A machshava problem that also
does not pre-date, it comes at the
time of shechita, and therefore and that
should be like chutz limkomo. Now, at
least that's reasonable, but it predates chutz
lizmano, right, but at least then, okay,
so now the arguments are pretty much
equal, right? In both cases you have
a machshava psul, one has kares, one
doesn't, but chutz lizmano is in general
more similar to chutz limkomo. In one
case by shelo lishmo the bread is
not sanctified, chutz lizmano it is. It
seems like a pretty evenly weighted which
one, if anything our intuition would be
more to say chutz limkomo goes with
chutz lizmano. Right, exactly, and they're both
the same parsha in the Torah, etc.
So although it still seems that Rabbi
Yehoshua is making an improved argument, for
us I think it would still seem
that Rabbi Eliezer has the better position.
But surprisingly let's look at the next
line of this braita. V'shatak Rabbi Eliezer.
Rabbi Eliezer had no response. And the
Gemara's going to say not only did
he have no response to say like
okay it's a draw, the Gemara's going
to interpret his silence to mean that
in the end he admitted to Rabbi
Yehoshua that you're right, that actually we
should learn it out that way and
we should say that actually is does
not kidesh ha-lechem. Now what is the
logic here? What is the logic, there
are two models, they're both machshava, one
is kidesh one is lo kidesh. Again,
why should I think learn it more
from shelo lishmo than from chutz lizmano?
So Tosfos says, and this is a
long Tosfos, he's dealing with other problems,
but one thing he says, which is
also what I was sort of thinking,
is let me also reframe the question.
Forget just like why learn it more
from one than the other. What is
the logic to say that chutz lizmano,
which is a greater psul, it's yesh
bo kares, right, that that should still
have the power to kadesh ha-lechem, but
chutz limkomo, which in our mind is
just like a weaker version of pigul
and is not kares, that somehow doesn't
sanctify the bread. It's ironic. So the
one thing that I think you can
say to this is, if you remember
one of the funny things about pigul
is we say a phrase of mirtzeh
l'pigulo. That the idea of pigul is
it's lo yeratzeh, which means that other
than the pigul it has to be
considered like it's fit for ritzuy, it's
fit for be received. And that basically
when we deal with pigul we look
at it, we're able to bracket the
pigul element to say that if it
weren't for the pigul it would be
mirtzeh, and that's what allows it to
be pigul, its potential to be mirtzeh
if you were to bracket the pigul.
So when it comes to pigul we
actually are able to suspend the idea
of pigul to evaluate it as whether
it's still mirtzeh. Mirtzeh l'pigulo. So that's
basically what Tosfos says, that's why pigul
could kidesh ha-lechem but not chutz limkomo,
because the whole within pigul we say
is it mirtzeh l'pigulo? Would it be
mirtzeh without, so we look at it,
we're able to look at it by
bracketing the pigul and saying oh bracketing
the pigul it was a good shechita,
it was kadosh, it would have been
mirtzeh. Oh, so if that's true the
lechem is kadosh, because we're able to
suspend the disbelief. whereas by everything else,
shelo lishmo, chutz l'mkomo, the other psulim,
we never look at it through that
lens and therefore we just say it
was a pasul shechitah, lo kidesh halechem.
So that's like the best way to
explain it, but again, if you just
look at what the Gemara says, it's
crazy. You see that in Tosafot? I
know. We never and that's what Tosafot
tries to figure out, like we've never
seen these even in these questions about
whether it's kidesh or lo kidesh. Tosafot
says basically as far as the korban
is concerned, the shechitah would be equally
kadosh, the whole issue here is the
bread which is one degree removed. So
that's maybe where the difference plays out.
So that's what Tosafot also says why
we didn't see this. You say there's
a whole debate about the bread and
not? Right, well that's the question: kidesh
halechem. So Tosafot also says the reason
we never saw this I know. Well,
and Tosafot says the reason we never
saw this in Zevachim and we don't
see this in other Gemaras is because
this is a slight difference and it
only has impact when it comes to
its ability to affect something else, but
not in terms of the thing itself.
Anyway, that's what you have that this
way without having Tosafot's part, the way
the Gemara sounds, it sounds like pretty
much equal positions. If anything, our intuition
would have gone to say with Rabbi
Yehoshua to say that it's like chutz
l'zmano and it's lo kidesh halechem. Was
that Rabbi Yehoshua? Rabbi Eliezer! And nevertheless
the Gemara says that this says Rabbi
Eliezer was shatik, which means he agreed
to Rabbi Yehoshua. Now this is all
Rabbi Yehuda's version. According to Rabbi Yehuda's
version, the end of the story is
chutz l'mkomo is different than chutz l'zmano.
But according to Rabbi Meir's version, they're
the same. chutz l'zmano and chutz l'mkomo
is both kidesh halechem. So at least
with Rabbi Meir we could say the
world gets restored to its normal tilt
now because that's back to pigul and
chutz l'mkomo being the same thing. Okay,
so now we see that our mishna
is Rabbi Meir because according to our
mishna chutz l'zmano and chutz l'mkomo are
the same. Right, that's the beraita, right?
Right, chutz l'zmano and chutz l'mkomo are
the same and the whole debate is
about the ba'al mum. Let's take a
look now at the Gemara. So now
the Gemara says like this: ולרבי מאיר
מאי שנא שחטה ונמצאת טרפה דהוי פסולו
קודם שחיטה. What is the difference between
treifa where the psul predated and therefore
lo kidesh halechem, ומאי שנא שחטה ונמצאת
בעלת מום דלא הוי פסולו קודם שחיטה,
and how is that different from the
case of the mum, which also predated
the psulo kodem shechitah and it's now
it doesn't mean d'lo havi psulo, meaning
why should we not consider it to
be a case of psulo kodem shechitah?
Should it not be the same thing?
Should it not fit into that category?
Or why is it not fitting into
that category and therefore you should say
lo kidesh halechem? Why is ba'al mum
any different than treifa? Very good question.
So let's see what the Gemara says.
And it's only a question according to
Rabbi Meir, because Rabbi Yehuda says it
is the same as treifa, but Rabbi
Meir says they debate ba'al mum. So
according to Rabbi Meir that they debate
ba'al mum, why? What's special about ba'al
mum? So the Gemara says, and it's
only a question according to Rabbi Eliezer,
according to this version who says it's
fine. Right, what's but yes, what's the
reason of the one who says it's
not like ba'al mum? So the Gemara
says: בדוקין שבעין ואליבא דרבי עקיבא. No,
we're talking only about a particular type
of a mum, about like a cataract
of the eye, which is very not
noticeable, and according to Rabbi Akiva, and
who cares that it's not so noticeable?
So the Gemara says because Rabbi Akiva
says when it's a non-noticeable mum like
that, אם עלו לא ירדו. If it
was put on the mizbe'ach, you don't
take it down. So you see we're
getting a whole finally getting back to
Zevachim. Okay, so there was a whole
idea that there were psulim, many psulim,
that if you put it on the
mizbe'ach you don't take it down, but
there were some that were excluded, that
even if it's on the mizbe'ach you
take it down. And by the mum,
Rabbi Akiva distinguishes between obvious mumin where
even if it's on the mizbe'ach you
take it off, as opposed to this
type of a cataract where it was
so unnoticeable that it's able to stay
on the mizbe'ach, which is pretty funny
because halachically it doesn't have a different
status, but nevertheless its noticeability affects this
issue of lo kidesh halechem. Well, now
it does according to Rabbi Akiva. Prior
to that it didn't. One minute to
this issue about whether you come off.
So how is that relevant to this?
So it's relevant in the following way:
that who is the one that says
that ba'al mum is kidesh halechem? kidesh.
Rabbi Eliezer. That Rabbi Eliezer is saying,
look, even though this mum predated, it's
not such a devastating psul. It's a
psul that the korban could still in
some ways be sanctified enough and be
kasher enough that if it went on
the mizbe'ach it wouldn't have to come
off. So even if you didn't put
it on the mizbe'ach. So even if
you didn't put it on the mizbe'ach
because when you shecht a korban with
this mum, it could still in theory
go on the be left on the
mizbe'ach if it were put up. So
therefore the shechitah still powerful enough to
be kidesh halechem as opposed to if
it was an obvious mum where the
korban would be so pasul that it
could never it couldn't even stay on
the mizbe'ach, then it would not be
enough to sanctify. And so you understand
the logic, right? Where if we're asking
ourselves was this shechitah, even if the
korban is pasul, there's some psulim that
are very central and there's some psulim
that are more secondary and incidental. So
if it's a major problem like it
was a treifa, you can't say the
shechitah was meaningful, you can't say kidesh
halechem. So same similarly by a mum,
if it's a major mum I agree.
then the whole animal is posul, you
can't say kidasha lacha. But if it's
a trivial mum and that there would
be an element in which the korban
now would be okay, I mean not
that you'd be yotzei, but could be
left on the mizbeach, so that type
of a mum is considered more of
a sort of, you know, incidental psul,
not a central psul. And therefore, that
type of a thing is enough to
say kidasha lacha. Yeah, I always have
questions like this, you know, like if
that's really the case, why doesn't the
Mishna just say dukin sheba'ayin, right. I
agree with you, I think that that's
not pshat of the Mishna, I think
pshat in the Mishna is whether it's
a psul based on the korban status
or a that at least within Rabbi
Eliezer, or psul that it wasn't even
a shechita. But what Rabbi Eliezer is
saying is look, the shechita was kasher,
it was done technically correctly, and you
know, it wasn't just treifa. So if
you have an introduce a new psul
like chutz lizmano, chutz limkomo, mum, korban
types of psulim, that will not prevent
it from kidasha lacha. Yes, things will
be posul, but if you had a
good shechita, that's how I would have
said it, that it was a korban
psul versus a non-korban psul. That's not
what the Gemara is saying. The Gemara
is saying whether it's a type of
a psul that would keep it off
of the mizbeach. That, by the way,
also explains why we don't have to
be concerned about chutz lizmano and chutz
limkomo, because chutz lizmano and chutz limkomo
are not not concerned, but why it's
kidasha lacha, because those are types of
psulim that even when you put it
on the mizbeach, the animal gets to
stay on the mizbeach, you don't take
it off. However, that's not a universal
rule, because again, shelo lishma, remembering, if
it's not treated as a Toda, then
the lo kidasha lacha. But as I
said, I think the shelo lishma is
of a different category. I think once
you're not defining it as a Toda,
you can no longer have the connection
between the korban and the bread. Okay,
yes. Was it try to encourage people
from given korbanot so that make it
so that let's say someone wants to
shecht the korban but this internal thing?
I mean, at what point does it
become after inspection of the shechita or
what's inside? Yeah, there's nothing you can
do about it. If you discovered that
it's a treifa after you shecht it,
you could have done everything right and
it could still be not good. But
it's encouraging. I guess that's true, you're
right, you're right. It's a bit of
a question. I think when they had
free range animals there were a lot
less treifas than there were today. But,
but yes, I think that that's right.
Or even more, because then wolves and
then attacks, okay, that would be true.
But I still think, I still think
that the conditions that they have today
include whatever. But anyway, it's a good
point that you can do everything right
and you could still have trouble. The
same now and if you were just
shechting it for the meat, then even
though there's going to be a percentage
of treifas you could always sell it
to a non-Jew. Once the korban has
been sanctified and it's a treifa, you're
right, then the whole thing you have
to let the whole thing go as
a loss. So it's a good point,
it's a good point. It's discouraging. I
know, I can't say anything about that,
it's a good point. It would be
okay to bring another korban? What? It
would be okay? If it's lo kidasha
lacha, in the scenario of lo kidasha
lacha, then right, then you can still
preserve the bread for another korban, correct.
And if it is? And if it's
kidasha and the korban is posul, that's
the worst of both worlds, because it
was kidasha, it was linked to the
korban, the korban is posul, you've got
to let that it becomes nifsal belina
and then burn it and destroy it.
But what's the point of having the
bread? Because if it's lo kidasha, you
can use the bread for another korban.
Right, so again, kidasha lacha is not
a good thing here. When the korban
becomes posul, if the bread is kadosh,
you're stuck, it's kadosh, it's linked to
this korban, you can't use it, you've
got to let it be now burned,
destroyed, whatever. If it's lo kidasha, it's
still free to go use for another
korban. Okay, let's put it on the
side and bring another animal and then
everything works together. Exactly, exactly. And we're
going to see that in the next
Mishna as well. Give this to somebody
else or sell it to somebody else?
Sell it, I'm not sure, because if
it already has kedushas kli shares, I'm
not sure about what your rights are
to sell it. I understand, but like
you also can't sell your shelamim that
you sanctified to somebody else. Once it's
linked to you, I'm not sure, I'm
not sure about that, but you can
certainly use it yourself for another korban
that you're going to bring. Okay, so
the Gemara says like this. Let's take
a look. Rabbi Yehoshua, how would Rabbi
Yehoshua respond why he's not why even
with this psul of the dukin sheba'ayin,
he still says the bread is not
sanctified? So he would say the following.
כי אמר רבי עקיבא אם לא ירדו
בפסול דגופיה. That when it comes to
the psula degufei of the animal itself,
so because it's a, you know, a
relatively minor mum, we'll let the animal
stay on the mizbeach. אבל קדושי לחם
לא. To have the power to sanctify
the bread, any psul can get in
the way, because you know, that's a
derivative kedusha. So when it's the animal
itself, yes, it could be kadosh enough
that it stays on the mizbeach. But
to have the power to sanctify the
bread, even these little problems can interrupt
that and get in the way. Of
course, a problem like chutz lizmano chutz
limkomo doesn't get in the way, but
at least a problem that predates the
shechita, any small thing is enough to
get in the way. Okay, now the
Gemara goes on. אתמר חטאת ששחטה חוץ
לזמנה אם עלתה לא תרד. So chutz
limkomo now, if you shechted a Chatas
with a chutz lizmano, a pigul thought.
If it goes on the mizbeach, don't
take it down. Chutz limkomo, however, to
a chutz limkomo thought, Rava amar tered,
רבה אמר לא תרד. Rava says take
it down, Rabbah says don't take it
down. So here is the only place
where once again we are seeing a
decoupling of chutz lizmano and chutz limkomo,
and this drives Tosfos crazy because Tosfos
says there are explicit Beraitos in Shas
that say whether it's chutz lizmano or
chutz limkomo אם עלה לא תרד. So
what the heck are Rava and Rabbah
doing debating it here? And he really
tries to figure out a whole new
way of explaining it, in one case
as well, maybe they're not talking about
the korban, maybe they're talking about whether
if you put the bread up, but
that doesn't work because of chatas. Also
maybe we should switch the girsa to
say todah. So it's a very strange,
this gemara doesn't fit anything we've learned
in Zevachim. Okay, anyway, but that's what
you have, this debate about if it's
chutz limkomo, again, ironically, chutz lizmano because
it's pigul has a concept of meratzeh
lepigulo. So chutz limkomo ironically because it's
pigul more severe, but nevertheless אם עלה
לא תרד. Chutz limkomo which doesn't have
that concept of meratzeh lepigulo could be
that it's worse in that way, you
never look at it as if it
were kosher and therefore even if it's
put on the mizbeach take it down.
Okay, so that's the debate. Rava amar
tered, take it down, רבה אמר לא
תרד. Rava ke-Rabbi Yehoshua, now this sounds
like they are debating the Rabbi Yehoshua,
Rabbi Eliezer debate within Rabbi Yehuda. Rava
says like Rabbi Yehoshua that chutz limkomo
is a bigger problem and therefore come
down. Ve-Rabbah ke-Rabbi Eliezer, Rabbah says like
Rabbi Eliezer that it's the same as
pigul and therefore gets to stay up.
And then it says והדר ביה רבה
לגבי דרבא, Rabbah in the end wound
up agreeing to Rava, he reversed himself
and he agreed to Rava that he
said that chutz limkomo is different than
chutz lizmano. How do we know that?
מדהדר ביה רבי אליעזר לגבי דרבי יהושע,
since Rabbi Eliezer was silent to Rabbi
Yehoshua, presumably he accepted Rabbi Yehoshua's argument.
So therefore, logically therefore, that position no
longer is a legitimate position. So we
should assume that Rabbah winds up agreeing
with Rava, which means it's bizarre, which
means that we're going to assume that
chutz limkomo is different than chutz lizmano,
which is not what we ever assume
anywhere else. And this is only anyway
by Rabbi Yehuda's version of the debate.
So the gemara actually stops this. The
gemara says like this: ve-ika de-amrei, some
say no. אף על גב דהדר ביה
רבי אליעזר לגבי דרבי יהושע, even though
Rabbi Eliezer reversed himself for Rabbi Yehoshua
and said I admit that chutz limkomo
is different than chutz lizmano, רבה לגבי
דרבא לא הדר ביה. Rabbah did not
reverse himself to Rava when it comes
to the issue of whether you have
to bring the korban down off the
mizbeach or not. התם הוא דקאמר ליה
מדונינו משלא לשמו. There, the only reason
he agreed was because you could equally
learn out chutz limkomo from shelo lishmo
as you could from chutz lizmano. So
there was another competing model. A competing
model was shelo lishmo, which was a
pesul machshava, and in that case you
would say the bread does not become
kadosh. That's why he agreed because there
was a competing model. Aval hacha, here,
אי דיינת ליה משלא לשמו, even if
I were to compare it to shelo
lishmo, אם עלה לא תרד, it wouldn't
come down. He's saying they're different halachos.
The question of whether something goes off
the mizbeach is we already all pesulei
machshava get to stay on the mizbeach,
whether it's pigul, whether it's shelo lishmo,
any pesul that's a result of a
machshava we say אם עלה לא תרד.
So there's no reason we should treat
chutz limkomo any different. Okay, if there'll
be a difference maybe it'll be in
your case of kiddush halechem where already
there's a difference between a pigul thought
and a shelo lishmo thought. And it
ends with this which is again fascinating
because the gemara in the end says
at least within Rabbi Yehuda we could
be willing to admit that there's a
difference between chutz limkomo and chutz lizmano
when it comes to this issue of
kiddush halechem. It won't always play out
in other areas because other areas you
know we treat all thought cases the
same, but there are cases where it
might continue to play out. And again
this really bothers Tosfos because everywhere else
in Shas we never distinguish between chutz
limkomo and chutz lizmano. Now you could
say it's because we rule like Rabbi
Meir over Rabbi Yehuda. This is all
Rabbi Yehuda's version of the debate. Tosfos
has other ways to try to really
bracket this whole discussion and to say
this is an entire discussion just about
the bread, not about anything else. Although
the gemara mentioned a chatas, we'll switch
the girsa to say todah and like
Tosfos really wants to compartmentalize, and a
todah means a todah lechem le-todah. Right,
he has other ways of reading the
gemara, but he really wants to compartmentalize
it because it's a shocking gemara to
the ways in the past that we've
completely... And the actual halacha is normally
we've said it all before, it's chutz
lizmano, chutz limkomo, אם עלה לא תרד.
Right, absolutely. Okay, so yeah I think
we managed to get through all of
Rabbah and Rava so that asked me
the question and you have any idea
why there would be a difference between
a machshava of chutz lizmano? Oh, now
you're going to start asking pigul questions.
Again. Okay, not really. Obviously the psukim
are talking about, you know, you can't
say it's... well, one thing is, one
thing I would say is the following
but in a way maybe it begs
the question, which is normally, you know,
a way to think about pigul is
your thought is as if it happened,
meaning not that you're chayav as if
it happened but it makes the korban
as if it happened. So if you're
thinking about chutz lizmano and then you
eat it, what's the chiyuv for eating
notar, which is meat leftover chutz lizmano?
It's kares. So the chiyuv for eating
pigul, which is a chutz lizmano thought,
is also kares. What's the chiyuv for
eating meat that was taken out of
the Beis Hamikdash is not kares? It's
a kares for being makriv a korban
out of the Beis Hamikdash, there might
be me'ila for eating the meat outside
of the Beis Hamikdash, but it's not
exactly, it's not the same type of
kares. But of course that just begs
the question. There is something to do
with the fact that there was not
always a chutz l'mokom? Oh, that's interesting.
The Gemara does say that at times,
about the zman of the heter bamos.
The other thing that I would say
is maybe the opposite of the point
you made, is that, you know, in
general pigul is like everything has to
be perfect except this very narrowly defined
thought. It has to be mirtza l'pigulo,
you can't have other problems, not every
bad thought, only like a very narrowly...
so pigul is almost like you just
missed the mark. It was all perfect
except you blew it here. And maybe
you know, there's somehow some power to
the idea that it was so close
and yes, yet it missed it. And
I think maybe that could be a
way of thinking about the difference of
chutz lizmano and chutz limkomo. The boundary
of space is very obvious. So the
idea of out of the space is
a much more obvious invalidity than the
idea of just waiting and doing it
tomorrow. So maybe the sense that somehow
it's a more subtle problem, I know
it's like I'm just, again, I'm sort
of begging the question but I do
think that that's an element of the
pigul, that like everything is right and
the problem is just, you know, you
just missed it this way, and that
therefore there's some greater severity in that
rather than some obvious problem. You know,
but again, it's a good question and
I don't know. So let's now finish
up at least till the... let's see
the mishna. Schachta shelo lishma. It was
schachta shelo lishmo. Then as we said
that does not kadesh halechem. We learned
it out from a pasuk. Amar Rav
Papa, שבקה תנא דידן איל נזיר. So
he's a little bothered because we also
included in the shelo lishmo that the
bread isn't sanctified the relationship of the
bread not only to the toda but
to the eil miluim and the shnei
kivsei atzeres. So he says why did
you go to miluim which is just
historic, why didn't you talk about the
eil nazir? Remember we also mentioned yesterday,
the shelamim of a nazir also comes
with bread. So why not talk about
that which is at least a practical
halacha, I mean practical to the degree
that any of this is practical? Anyway,
שבקה תנא דידן איל נזיר, our tanna
abandoned the case of eil nazir deshchiach
which is more common and should have
been mentioned, ונקט איל המילואים and he
talked about the eil miluim which is
only of historic interest. And so that's,
you know, he's noting that. And then
the Gemara says so why was that
true? DeTanna Didan, what was the motivation
of our tanna? Ikar milsa nakat. He
wanted to go with the first occurrence.
The first time you have bread linked
to a shelamim is by the eil
miluim, so he wanted to refer back
to that, although it was only of
historic interest. Okay, now that is the
shechita sanctifying the bread and what type
of shechita if it's pasul still sanctifies
the bread. Now we continue with this
whole, with the relationship again of the
shechita and the bread. Wait, but the
miluim carried forward to any time that
a kohen... Oh, the mincha that was
brought. That's true, but not the bread
that came with the shelamim, but the
concept of like the minchas chavitin of
the Kohen Gadol, that aspect of it
also became a mincha that any kohen
brings when he is initiated into the
avoda. But not the bread that came
with the shelamim. You're right, the Gemara
sort of conflated them but we... it's
just as a mincha. Okay, now we
move beyond the bread to another thing
that comes with the korban and comes
with a lot more korbanos, which is
nesachim, the wine. We could also talk
about the minchas nesachim that comes with
free will sacrifice, a free will korban,
shelamim or an olah, whatever, what do
you bring with it? You bring with
it a certain mincha, actually not just
free will, well, it's even if you're
not taking a neder, any olah and
shelamim. You bring with it the... this
is why we say in the Musaf,
you know, מנחתם ונסכיהם כמשפטם שלשה עשרונים
לפר ושני עשרונים לאיל. So it's a
certain mincha, flour and water and and
and oil and there's a certain amount
of wine, so that too is linked
to the korban. But the link is
not the same because the general principle
is נסכיהם אפילו מכאן ועד עשרה ימים.
That if you can bring the korban
today and you can bring the nesachim
tomorrow. So as opposed to the bread
which is tightly linked and it has
to be coming today and you have
to eat it on the same day,
this type of a thing can come
on a different day. So what is
now the relationship going to be between
the shechting of the korban and the
nesachim? Maybe different than the relationship to
the bread. So let's look now at
the Mishna. Hanesachim shekiddshu bicheli, so the
Nesachim which you did put it into
a Kli Shares and they were sanctified
and now you Shechted the Korban. So
how is that defined? Venimtza zevach pasul,
the Korban is Pasul. So אם יש
זבח אחר יקריבו עמו, you can bring
it with another Korban, you're not stuck.
V'im lav, and if there isn't another
Korban and it already was sanctified in
the vessel, what do you have to
do? Yifslu belinah, then you have to
just let then it becomes Pasul, it
stays overnight, it's Pasul, you can't use
it. So if you were to ask
what is the simple sense of this
Mishna? Is the Shechitas hazevach, does it
sanctify the Nesachim or not? What would
you say? No. No, right? It seems
like it's saying here the Shechita has
nothing to do with the Nesachim. They
were sanctified in the Kli. So now
it's not about the Shechita, they have
some independence. As I said before, they
can come on a different day. So
therefore, if you can't use this Korban,
who cares? Doesn't affect this status. Go
use it with another Korban. If there's
no other Korban to use it for
and it was already sanctified in the
vessel, so because it already had Kedushas
kli, it's going to become Pasul belinah.
So therefore, if you can't find something
by the end of the day, then
come night it'll become Pasul. Why? Because
it was already sanctified not by the
Shechita, the Shechita was Pasul, it was
sanctified by the Kli. So the simple
sense of this Mishna is exactly to
distinguish this from the Lechem. This is
about Kedushas kli, not about Shechita. Of
course, the entire Gemara now we're going
to look at insists that this is
Kedusha by the this is Shechitas hazevach
and is now going to try to
make sense of the Mishna by taking
that approach. What kind of a Kli
would it have been in? Some type
of a Kli Shares that was like
that to contain the wine. I mean
the same kind of bowls used for
the blood or a different one? Hopefully
a different one. Hopefully they washed it
well. Okay. So let's take a look.
So the Gemara says, Amar Zeiri, so
Zeiri now makes this very complicated because
Zeiri insists that it is similar to
the bread. אין הנסכים מתקדשים אלא בשחיטת
הזבח. So, oh my God, seems to
be the opposite of the Mishna. The
Nesachim also only become sanctified through the
slaughtering of the Korban. Mai ta'ama? What's
the reason? Amar kra, the Pasuk says,
Zevach unesachim, Davar yom beyomo, the Korban
and its Nesachim, it links them. Okay,
now let's see if Zeiri can work
with our Mishna. Tnan, our Mishna says,
הנסכים שקדשו בכלי ונמצא זבח פסול אם
יש זבח אחר יקריבו עמו ואם לאו
יפסלו בלינה, our Mishna. מאי לאו דאפסיל
בשחיטה? It sounds like the Shechita was
Pasul. And what does it mean that
the Shechita was Pasul? It means that
there was either a Pasul machshava or
maybe it was a Treifa, maybe it
was a Mum, but it actually sounds
like the Shechita was Pasul. Now if
you're right, Zeiri, why can you now
use it for another Korban? Why didn't
it become if the Shechita sanctifies, then
if the Shechita is Pasul, it should
also transfer the Pasul if it's linked
to the Shechita? So if the Shechita
was Pasul, how now can you use
it for another Korban? It says it
was found to be Pasul at the
Shechita. So it says, no, D'ifsil bizrika.
When we say that it was found
to be Pasul, it doesn't mean the
Pasul occurred at the Shechita, the Pasul
occurred at the Zrika. So at the
Shechita it already became sanctified and now
there's a problem that comes at the
Zrika. But that's okay, it already became
sanctified, and now if you can't use
it for this Korban, use it for
another. Now that's already bizarre because if
you're giving weight to the Shechita, you
would also think that it doesn't just
sanctify it but that it links it
to the Korban. If you're giving weight
to the Shechita, if you don't give
weight to the Shechita, it can be
a free agent, but if you're giving
weight to the Shechita, it should link
it. Okay, so that's going to be
very bizarre. So let's see where the
Gemara, right, that's the question. But let's
see where the Gemara says D'ifsil bizrika.
So the Gemara says, K'man, who is
this going like? כרבי דאמר שני דברים
המתירין מעלין זה בלא זה. Are you
saying it's going like Rebbi who says
when you have two things that are
Matir, one can work independent of the
other. What Rebbi is this? So of
course you will remember that about I
don't know two months ago we discussed
where if you had the two Kivsei
Atzeret and the bread, the Shtei Halechem,
so what if the Gemara says or
not the Gemara, the Braisa says, שחטה
לשמה וזרק דמה שלא לשמה? So there
was one opinion, רבי אלעזר בר רבי
שמעון, that says the bread only becomes
sanctified through the combination of the Shechita
and the Zrika, without both you have
nothing and the bread does not become
sanctified. Rebbi said, no, the bread became
sanctified with the Shechita even though the
Zrika was not correct and it's Kadosh,
but you can't it's not Ne'echal or
whatever it is. Okay, but at least
it worked somewhat independently. So Gemara saying
this is just the same idea. You're
saying we have Shechita and Zrika, you're
saying that the Shechita would be enough
by itself, that even though the Korban
only becomes Kasher with the Zrika, that
the Shechita by itself is one step
and would be enough to sanctify the
Nesachim according to you that the Nesachim
are linked to the Shechita. So the
Gemara says, is that what you are
saying? So the Gemara says, no, אפילו
תימא רבי אלעזר בר רבי שמעון, even
רבי אלעזר בר רבי שמעון that argues
with Rebbi over there. and says it's
either all or nothing, hacha b'mai askinan,
I'll get you all here as well.
It's a very special case. What's the
case? כגון שקיבל דמם בכוס ונשפך. You
slaughtered it correctly, you caught the blood
and the blood spilled, and therefore what?
So what? You still don't have the
second stage. But we're not done. Turn
the page. רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון סבר
לה כוותיה דאבוה d'amar כל העומד לזרוק
כזרוק דמי. Rebbe Shimon is of the
opinion that anything that is fit to
be thrown, the blood, it's like it's
already thrown. Now, it doesn't mean that
literally. It's not like oh so you
don't have to do zrikas hadam and
the korban is still kasher, right? You
actually require the act of zrika. Every
time you say it's as if, the
question is how much is it as
if? But it's as if enough that
we could say that the kedusha that
emerges from it because all that was
left was the zrika and it was
fit for the zrika, at that moment
it was enough to be instilled with
the kedusha. Now, that is different than
if I go ahead and I do
zrika shelo lishma. I actually invalidate that
stage. Then I can't say oh retroactively
it was k'zaruk dami because I've actually
now invalidated that stage. But if I
never invalidated it, I just spilled it
and never did it, so for some
reason that is still enough to say
well it got to that point, that
was enough to create the kedusha. Okay.
So yes, maybe you need two stages
to create the kedusha, but as long
as it got to the point where
it could have been done, that was
enough to create the kedusha as long
as you don't ruin it afterwards. As
long as you spill it rather than
bezoreik shelo lishma. What's our wait... so
oppose... so there the case where it
originally was... there it was zoreik shelo
lishma... there the case of Rebbe and
רבי שמעון בר אלעזר was שחטה לשמה
ונזרק שלא לשמה. You actually did the
zrika incorrectly. That he said is a
problem. There you ruined it. But if
you didn't ruin it, you just never
did it, then we'll sort of give
you credit, you got to the stage
where it was fit, and that's enough
to create the kedusha. Okay. So now
what are we saying? We are saying
is rather than reading this mishna nice
and simply that the shchitah has nothing
to do with the kedusha of the
nesachim, we're saying it does have to
do with the kedusha of the nesachim.
Why then if the shchitah was pasul
can I use it for something else?
Very, very special case. The shchitah really
wasn't pasul, the shchitah was kasher, but
not only that the zrika wasn't pasul,
it's just the blood was spilled. Go
tell me how the idea of spilling
the blood fits the language of nimtza
zevach pasul. Okay, it doesn't fit the
language at all. But anyway, the blood
was spilled and therefore the bread became
kadosh and therefore you can now use
it for another korban. That still asks
the question: Okay, I understand that it's
kadosh. Why can I transfer the korban?
Shouldn't it be linked to the korban
if it's all about the kedusha? So
that's what the gemara is now going
to turn into. Amar Mar, so now
we taught: אם יש זבח אחר יקרבו
עמו. If there's another korban use it
with that korban, this wine. So now
the gemara, so now it's going to
turn to this question about if it's
linked to it, how can I really
transfer which korban it's related to? Veha'amar
Rav Chisda, doesn't Rav Chisda say שמן
שהפרישו לשום מנחה זו פסול לשום מנחה
אחרת? If you designate oil for one
mincha you can't use it for another
and there it was only designated here
the whole shchitah which was mekadesh according
to the Iri. So amar Rav Yannai,
Rav Yannai says no, לב בית דין
מתנה עליהם. beis din stipulates and says
אם הוצרכו הוצרכו ואם לאו יהיו לזבח
אחר. beis din stipulates for anytime anybody
brings wine with their korban that if
it were... if you wind up using
it for the korban great and if
not we'll say from the very outset
that it is not linked to that
korban, we'll make like a stipulation and
say it will be free to use
for another korban. לב בית דין מתנה
אמאי by private korban? Yes, that's a
very good... I'd say that if anything
it would be with the communal korban
if like you know... right, right. So...
I think... beis din all of a
sudden? Why the rabbis? What does beis
din have to do with it? Right.
So that's similar to you know Michael's
question as you... you know... lev beis...
yeah, I mean although the gemara which
is also interesting, you know again sort
of the rabbinic read of the mikdash,
they're always inserting beis din which is
like rabbis into the mikdash as the
ultimate authority in the mikdash. But anyway,
it's one thing to say that you
could believe that in like a context
of a communal korban Michael's actually correct
and very often we do say לב
בית דין מתנה by a communal korban.
I'm trying to remember because Rashi or
Tosafos, somebody actually raises that issue about
communal versus non-communal. One minute. But the
authority just has the authority whether it's
the rabbis or the Kohanim or whatever
it is that's in charge of the
whole... right, it's sort of like when
you say כל דמקדש אדעתא דרבנן מקדש.
Rabbis get to define everything about halachic
life. But anyway I do think somebody
does bring out a difference between communal
and private. I'll have to check for
it. So let's see how the gemara
answers this, okay? So the gemara says
oh we somehow stipulate and say that
if a problem occurs it will never
have been sanctified for that korban. Ah
that's what the gemara says. So the
gemara says אם הוצרכו הוצרכו ואם לאו
יהו לזבח אחר. I hachi says the
gemara shemen nami. Let's say the same
by the oil. You sanctified oil for
your korban but if somehow some problem
occurred you have a right to use
it for a different different Mincha, so
the Gemara says שמן גופא דמנחה הוא.
No, shemen is actually the ingredient, the
direct ingredient of the Mincha. You can't
say, oh, this is going to be
used for something else. It wasn't like
something that was used for a Mincha;
it was actually a part of the
Mincha. So we are not going to
so re-stipulate what you have said if
you're not just assigning it to something
but you're making it a part of
something. So if it's a part of
the Mincha, it can now not become
a part of another Mincha. But the
Gemara is still not satisfied. If it's
all about Beis Din, Beis Din can
do whatever they want. So the Gemara
says like this, so the Gemara says
after this gufa deminecha hu, וליתנו עליה
דנפקו לחולין. Okay, so if you're saying
you can't say use it for another
Mincha because it was not just assigned
to a Mincha but it was Mincha
X and it now can't become Mincha
Y, it can't become another Mincha. Nevertheless,
why don't you just say, oh, if
some problem occurred, then it would never
have been kadosh from the get-go, okay,
and at least let me get my
shemen back. Okay, so the Gemara says
וליתנו עליה דנפקו לחולין, let let it
now go out to chulin. No, גזירה
שמא יאמרו מוציאין מכלי שרת לחול. People
will see that it was sanctified in
a kli shares; they won't understand Beis
Din stipulation; they won't understand that there
was a problem that it couldn't be
used in the original Mincha, and they'll
think that something that was sanctified in
kli shares can become chulin, and that's
not true. You can't be podeh. No,
because the other case we didn't say
it was chulin. We said use it
for another korban. Right, so then people
will think that I can use it
for one korban to another in regular
cases. Ah, השתא נמי גזירה שמא יאמרו
נסכים שפירושו לשם זבח זה יהיו לשם
זבח אחר. See, Micah, you're right, the
Gemara. Ah, so the Gemara says people
make a mistake here and say nesachim
for one thing you can just reassign
it; they won't understand it was a
special case and that it was all
because of lev Beis Din. So the
Gemara says התניא מתתיה בן יהודה, no,
because Matas bin Yehuda teaches כגון שהיה
זבח זבוח באותה שעה, that it was
already another korban was slaughtered. So it's
not like you're waiting around, hey, does
anybody have another Todah, we've got, does
anybody have another korban, we've got some
nesachim available? No, you had another korban
right there and you immediately use it.
So nobody would, nobody would see that
anything strange had happened, right? You know,
they don't sort of see, oh, it
was being moved from here to there.
You slaughtered, that was the korban and
you just now get the nesachim. Right.
So therefore the Gemara says that's why
we're not afraid if this very special
case. So the Gemara says, you know,
come on, give me a break, it's
not what the Mishna's talking about. The
Gemara says אבל אין זבח זבוח באותה
שעה, if there's no, you're telling me
if there's no other korban already shechted
and ready to use the nesachim, mai,
what would you say? Yipslu belina? We
would have to let it become pasul
belina; we couldn't reassign it? Adtani seifa,
since our end of our Mishna says
אם לאו יפסלו בלינה, so if it,
if there's no other korban, then it
becomes pasul belina, liplog velisni bedidi. Don't
just tell me it's about having a
korban or not having a korban. What
it really should say is bamei devarim
amurim, when can I use the nesachim
for another korban? שהיה זבח זבוח באותה
שעה, if there was already a korban
slaughtered and waiting for it. אבל אין
זבח זבוח באותה שעה לא, then I
couldn't use it. So the Gemara says
hachi nami ka'amar, that really is what
it means. Bamei devarim amurim, when is,
when can I use the nesachim for
another korban? שהיה זבח זבוח באותה שעה,
it was already slaughtered. אבל אין זבח
זבוח באותה שעה, if it wasn't already
slaughtered, נעשה כמי שיפסלו בלינה ודמיהן. Right,
now exactly. Now, besides that it's reading
a lot into the Mishna and this
is all very hard to, you know,
buy into all of this, and it
all argues that really Iri's read is
a very, you know, forced read, and
the simple sense of the Mishna is
that it's not linked. But again, see
what the Gemara's now saying. It's very
interesting how the Gemara's now considering what
happened. The shechita of the korban sanctifies
the wine, okay, not to the point
that it's, that well, the way they're
sort of framing it is, it is
maybe linked to the korban, but Beis
Din somehow is able to redefine that.
Well, which is another korban, right? But
well, that's to be concerned about a
maris ayin. And when they redefine it,
when they redefine it, they're redefining it
to a korban that was already shechted.
So this korban now that was already
shechted, its shechita had nothing to do
with this wine. You need the shechita
to sanctify the wine. The shechita of
korban A sanctified this wine; now you're
going to use this wine for korban
B that was already shechted, and its
shechita was totally unrelated. So the link
of the wine to the korban is
very bizarre. Now, normally I would say
who cares, maybe it doesn't have to
be linked. But if you're insisting that
shechita is what creates the kedusha, it
is quite fascinating that we can then
decouple it from the first korban and
reassign it to another korban to which
it never had any relationship with. Okay,
so it's all of this is the
baggage that we get besides the textual
problems if we assume that the shechita
of sanctifies the nesachim. The simple sense
of the Mishna is that it does
not. Did people bring their wine or
was the wine there? No, they had
to bring their own wine. Okay, there
were some special cases that the Beis
Hamikdash provided the wine like if a
nazir brought a korban. So the second
shechita, the guy would go home with
the wine he brought? The second shechita,
I mean because he already brings his
wine anyway. Oh. Sell it to the
next guy. Sell it to the next
guy, I guess. Right, right, right. That's
a good question. Yeah, go home with
it. It depends whether he had sanctified
it or not sanctified it. Was already
shechted yet. Oh, yeah, that's a good
point. Yeah, that's a good point too,
if the korban was already shechted, it's
already sanctified the wine that it had.
Yeah, you'd have to imagine a case
but you could bring wine on a
different day, אפילו מכאן ועד עשרה ימים.
So therefore, it could be a case
where the guy was planning on bringing
it later, he says, \"Don't worry, we
got some extra wine here.\" But again,
that very fact that you can bring
the nesachim later also should really prove
that you can't say the shechita was
m'kadesh. And I believe that the Gemara
in another place, I'd have to check,
after that, on Ze'iri's psak, Ze'iri's only
talking about a circumstance where they came
together. When they came apart, he would
be modeh that the shechita is m'kadesh.
But again, all of that argues to
say that it's never m'kadesh, that it
always sort of is kedusha exists independent,
which is again the simple sense of
our Mishna. Okay, let's just wrap this
up. So the Gemara says like this,
ומי אית ליה לרבי שמעון לב בית
דין מתנה עליהן? Since we're saying that
Rabbi Elazar ben Rabbi Shimon held like
Rabbi Shimon, we're trying to say this
all works within Rabbi Shimon, although that's
questionable. Does he really hold of this
principle of לב בית דין מתנה עליהן?
ואמר רב אידי בר אבין אמר רב
עמרם אמר רבי יצחק אמר רבי יוחנן
תמידין שלא הוצרכו לציבור. If the tzibur
did not need the temidim, meaning you
bought your tamid with the communal funds
and then for some reason you had
extra. Why? Your tamid got lost, so
you separated another one and then you
found the one that got lost. Now
you have an extra korban lying around
here. What are you going to do
with it? And here it's communal. So
here the idea of lev beis din
makes a lot more sense. So what,
so they said according to Rabbi Shimon,
ein nifdin tmimim. You cannot redeem it
because it doesn't have a mum. ולדברי
חכמים נפדין תמימים. The Chachamim let you
redeem it even though it doesn't have
a mum. Why? Because of the principle
of לב בית דין מתנה עליהן. Although
you can never redeem something without a
mum, here we will stipulate that if
somehow this happens, and here particularly it's
a communal korban and communal funds, we'll
retain the right to redeem it. So
you see that Rabbi Shimon does not
say לב בית דין מתנה עליהן. And
our whole discussion before involved Rabbi Shimon.
So how could we introduce the idea
of lev beis din in the discussion
before if Rabbi Shimon doesn't hold of
it? Because you can do something about
it. So the Gemara says, שאני התם
דאית להו תקנתא בראייה. I don't know
if that's what you meant, but it
says over there you could have fixed
the problem. Why? Because you could graze.
Okay, great. See, like always you're right,
the Gemara, you could use that tamid
that you couldn't use now, you could
wait till it gets a mum and
then you'll redeem it. So there's a
solution. And Tosafot says precisely that, you
can even bring it as an olah
on the mizbe'ach for kayitz hamizbe'ach. So
there there's a solution, so we're not
going to say lev beis din. Here
there's no solution. If you don't let
me use it for another zevach, I'm
going to have to let it become
pasul, and that's why we say. So
again, all of this was very complicated
thing to try to defend how Ze'iri's
position against our Mishna that says the
shechita is m'kadesh. But the simple sense
of the Mishna is to contrast it
to the bread. By the bread, the
shechita is m'kadesh, by the nesachim because
they can come on a later date
and are not closely linked, they're not
m'kadesh until the zevach. But that's not
what Ze'iri says. All right.